so we have seen that moving from one bit
predictor to two bit predictor improves
things primarily because the one-off
occurrences of the other behavior are
not going to change our complete
decision so now the question is if the
increase in the predictor sighs this way
worked why not do the three bit
predictor or a four bit predictor the
bad part of using more bits per
predictor is that the cost goes up in
proportion to how many bits we need we
still need to have the same number of
predictor entries in order so that each
branch has its own predictor entry and
not share it with another branch it
behaves differently so for the same
number of entries we will have this
doubles the cost this is gonna add
another 50% to the cost and so on so we
are increasing the cost it might be
worth it if the prediction accuracy is
improving so the good side is that
sometimes the branch prediction accuracy
does improve as you go to three bits or
four bits when well adding three bits or
four bits is gonna increase the
hysteresis so for a longer time
we will keep guessing the old way even
though decisions are going the other way
so really the only time when this is
good is when anomalous outcomes come in
streaks if you have a streak of for
example not taking all of the time and
then it happens that you have taken
taken very often after that and then
again not taken for awhile then actually
having a tree bit predictor would solve
the problem of being convinced the other
way when the taken taken happens but the
real question is how often do we really
have in real programs that anomalous
outcomes come in streaks and the answer
is not very often so what we might have
is that the tree bit predictor might be
worth it but definitely not the 4 bit
predictor so somehow we really want to
have either a 2 bit predictor or a 3 bit
predictor and most of the time we're
just fine with the 2 bit predictor we're
getting most of the benefits we would
get with more bits for a lower cost so
we really should stay with the 2 bit
predictor and maybe move to 3 bits if we
really really want to but if moving to
more bits like this is not helping us
then the question becomes but how do we
then improve prediction beyond
two bit predictor we have already seen
that neither one bit nor two bit
predictor work really well when we have
things like not taken taken not taken
taken etc and now a human being that
looks at this sequence not taken taken
not taken taken etc will correctly guess
that the next outcome here will probably
be not taken followed by taken and so on
so this branch turns out to be perfectly
predictable it's just that it's not
predictable with a one bit or two bit
predictor